[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
hello everybody Welcome to the ask
Abhijit show we are back live this
weekend I hope you have all been doing
very well and it's great to be back live
amongst you all
so as always let's see who all is there
on the live chat I can see a whole lot
of people sabana Arpita
saitama saurabh Ashwin rishikesh Vivek
samrat Sagar CBJ Dutch Wonderland
Raj
[Laughter]
an one
Wheels
Tamil nandi Dr Amit
sumnat or Lotus vishesh sumiya Jain
janak ujjwal dhruv Kumar DK pramod yadav
[Music]
shivansh Forum exasperated
and so many so many other people it's
it's great to be back amongst you all
live again geopolitical Dubai Maximus
Prime kill fish just man Raj Singh
uh
Divya and so on uh
thank you so much for being on this live
uh on this live stream so with that said
let's go into the questions as you know
today I'm gonna take questions from the
comments
uh I've done a few of the live chat live
streams in the past in the past few
weeks there was a break of a couple of
weeks because I was troubling but yes so
today we're gonna take questions from
the comments the Corbin the questions
you have asked in the comments so let's
get into it right away
what's question number one
question number one is by Tata dripat
uh Anthony albane's boss comment on
Prime Minister Modi those are the those
are just words what do you think he why
do you think he said this yes so
recently uh Prime Minister Modi of India
visited Australia he was in Australia on
the I think the 23rd and the 24th of
this month May 2023
and over there he had these public
welcomes and public events in the Prime
Minister Albanese was with him the Prime
Minister of Australia and at some point
the Prime Minister of Australia made
this comment he called Prime Minister
Modi the boss so what was he referring
to I think he was referring to Bruce
Springsteen the American singer you know
he was a very very popular in the 70s
80s 90s and so on I think he's still
very popular and he was Bruce
Springsteen was nicknamed the boss
and he used to draw these enormous
crowds that's how popular he was so I
think the Australian prime minister was
referring to that when he called Mr Modi
the boss essentially he means that Prime
Minister Modi whenever he comes to
Australia draws enormous crowds the kind
of crowds the Australian prime minister
himself cannot draw in Australia so
that's why uh he made this comment
comment and that's what it uh was
referring to
so what do I think of this well it's a
nice comment but that's it's also it's
always nice to praise your guests and
say nice things about them right it's
it's a good manners it's a common
courtesy especially when you're uh when
you are hosting a visiting head of state
you say nice things about them so uh
it's a nice gesture it's a nice thing to
say but after all at the end of the day
uh words have no geopolitical meaning uh
implications unless they are made in a
very specific context
so uh in the past you know uh
Indian leaders of the past have been
very susceptible to flattery Mr Modi is
not one of those leaders he's a new he's
a new kind of guy he's a very different
uh
kind of leader it's uh you cannot get
things done
by you know flattering him but anyway
this is something that historically has
worked with Indian leaders so it's it's
something that the West still does and
you will say that Australia is not the
West it's in the Eastern hemisphere it's
in the southern part below the equator
south of the Equator well Australia is
when we talk about the West we're
talking about a political or
geopolitical term not a geographical
term an Australia and New Zealand are
part of the West even though they are
physically geographically in the east so
uh
so that's what prime minister Albanese
meant by calling Mr Modi the boss he was
praising Mr Modi he was saying a nice
thing about him he was comparing him
with a mega star Bruce Springsteen and
that's what it was it has no
geopolitical meaning or implication it's
just you know you're praising the person
you're hosting the the world leader
you're hosting so that's all it is
there's nothing more to it than that
okay next question let's try and take as
many questions as we can today and then
hopefully even some from the live chat
if you get some time
ishan Bhai says your thoughts on our
so-called close Ally Saudi Arabia
boycotting G20 Summit in Kashmir so I
would like to once again urge my dear
viewers let's not get emotional
when it comes to geopolitics emotions
have no place in geopolitics
okay so what's the deal so see why am I
saying this because the the language
here so called close the lie it's it's
kind of sarcastic and kind of hurt
there's some emotion there so understand
uh how things work
Saudi Arabia has excellent relations
with India
under Prime Minister Modi we have
developed very close very warm very
friendly uh and and and overall very
good relations with many of the gulf
Nations Saudi Arabia the UAE and so on
right Oman and so on
now it doesn't mean that we are allies
it means that we have lots of shared
geopolitical and other interests but we
don't have any official Alliance okay so
that's number one secondly
yes Saudi Arabia did not attend the the
G20 event it was not the summit this was
not the G20 Summit that happened in
Kashmir it was one of the G20 events
there are more than 100 G20 events
happening all over India this year it
will all culminate with the summit
meeting the final meeting it will be in
winter this year Autumn or winter so the
event that happened in Kashmir was one
of the tourism events
and Saudi Arabia did not participate in
it well they chose not to why are we
making a big deal of it I mean I'm sure
there is some geopolitical reason and
I'll come to that but listen
I attended the uh
the s20 science initiation meeting in
pondicherry I think it was in February
or March most likely end of February or
beginning March thereabouts this year it
was a G20 event the initiation meeting
of the s20 dialogue of the s20 stream of
the G20 thing so I was there in
pondicherry in the initiation meeting
and the Saudi did not send a delegate
so are we gonna start complaining the
Saudi Arabia boycotted the science event
the s20 event in pondicherry
are we going to start complaining about
that so let's see things
more holistically
let's see the big picture
so that's how this did not send somebody
in any Delegate for the s20 event so
it's not a boycott it's just that they
chose to skip this you know when I do
earlier I used to do these live streams
based on various topics I used to do
geopolitics themed live streams in which
I will only take geopolitics questions
then I used to do history theme live
streams in which I only took history
history questions and then I used to do
these science live streams and I always
saw that well where I'll do geopolitics
or history live streams I will get x
amount of live viewers when I do science
it's like one third of that because
nobody is interested in science
so overall in the world very few people
find Science interesting of course
science is very important for for
progress but overall there is less
interest in science so maybe the Saudis
found that science is not interesting
and let's not send a delegate for that
event maybe it's that so now coming to
the tourism event well you will see
tweets by various Arab influencers Arab
people wearing the dish Dasha and all
that you know the Arabic traditional
dress in Kashmir saying that look how
beautiful kashmiri is uh this is not
Switzerland it's not something else it's
it's India it's Kashmir that's what
various Arab influencers have done on
social media uh so it's not like the
Arabs are supporting Pakistan or
supporting China I mean individually now
why let's come to not the geopolitical
thing why did Saudi Arabia choose not to
send a delegate for this specific event
well clearly there must be possibly
possibly a geopolitical angle to it
the Chinese
are investing in Saudi Arabia they are
buying investing in the sense that they
are buying lots of Saudi oil oils are
producing the Americans are no longer
buying Saudi oil so the Saudis need
other buyers and China is one of the
major buyers so is India
okay and recently there was some kind of
uh agreement a bunch of agreements that
were that were agreed upon between
President Xi Jinping and the Saudi uh
government when Xi Jinping visited a few
months ago right so clearly the Saudis
uh they they uh they give a lot of
importance to their relations with China
and similarly with India as well so I am
sure the Chinese must have
told the Saudis to stay away from this
maybe pressurize them in the Saudis
prudently thought it you know a good
thing to do not to send a delegate it
doesn't mean they are boycotting the
event they are taking part in various
other uh events as well they're just
staying away from controversy that's all
they are saying that's all they are
doing the Saudis are not anti-india the
Saudis actually overall if India were
much larger much more powerful much much
richer they would prefer India over
China and they would obviously want to
hedge their bets and spread the risk
overall but that's how it goes so most
likely the Saudis did not want to get in
embroiled in any unnecessary
geopolitical dispute or controversy
they're not taking this side or that
side they sting out of it
so it it is it doesn't mean that they
are boycotting the the summit or the
event they're just staying out of
controversy I'm sure there is Chinese
pressure so we need not look at it as
emotionally as some kind of backstabbing
or anything it's nothing it's no big
deal this is par for the course in
diplomacy and geopolitics we have to
understand they have compulsions the
same way that we also have compulsions
right
so that's how it that's how the
geopolitical game is played and we need
not we must not get emotional about
every little thing
always see the big picture overall in
the big picture of the India Saudi
Arabia relationship is excellent so
let's not because they made a certain
choice we didn't we don't need to you
know get emotional about it you know and
all that I mean if you look at India's
record in the United Nations we have
voted against Israel so many times
including in recent in recent uh
recently the last couple of years also
so do we want the Israelis to get all
emotional about this no right there are
certain compulsions or whatever reasons
I will not go into the Israel angle
right now so it's all about
you know uh
trading a very prudent path and
sometimes you don't do certain things it
doesn't mean that the relationship is
bad so look at it that way next
Tushar says hypothetically speaking if
there is a nuclear Russian nuclear
offensive on Ukraine then the
retaliation of the West would be from
the ground of the U.S or Ukraine that's
okay where will the retaliation of the
west from the West come from that's
question number one secondly how would
the bharatiya government react to it
would they announce a lockdown like step
okay hypothetically if there's a Russian
nuclear attack offensive on Ukraine
well first of all I think that is
extremely unlikely there is a certain
Red Line nobody wants to cross we nobody
wants to cross the nuclear threshold the
way the Americans did in 1945 nobody
wants to do such a thing the Russians
are not mad people they're not crazy
Russia is a very rational nation and Mr
Putin is not a Madman the way the
Western media portraitism is a very
rational person I mean see the
incredible restraint he has shown
compare that with what happened in World
War II
yeah who was the bad guy in World War II
it was Hitler do you see the behavior
Hitler showed and can you contrast it
with what with with the with the uh
actions Putin is taking enormous
contrast Putin is not a Madman he's a
very rational person he he knows exactly
what he wants to achieve and he knows
exactly what he doesn't want to do
so he's very clear about his objectives
so um so he's not crazy first of all
he's not a madman and I do not see him
crossing the nuclear threshold unless he
has no other option and the nuclear
threshold will be crossed only when
Russian soil itself will come under
threat and Russian territory may be in a
position that they will lose Russian
territory or or something like that
that's the only scenario in which I see
the Russians using nuclear weapons and
then they would use tactical nuclear
weapons to begin with
but hypothetically since we are dealing
with hypotheticals let's say there is a
Russian tactical uh nuclear strike
somewhere in Ukraine let's say then
where will the retaliation of the best
come from it will not come from the
ground of the U.S if you look at the map
and there are maps available on Google I
will not open and search for them it
will take time but the Americans have
nuclear weapons stashed away deployed on
European soil
there are nuclear weapons American
nuclear weapons in various parts of
Europe including in Turkey the Turks
have
American nuclear weapons deployed on
their territory and they're not in the
control of the Turks they are controlled
by Americans on Turkish territory
similarly there are other European
nations like Germany I expect
Netherlands and other nations so
essentially they have encircled Russia
in to a certain extent let's let's go to
the map oh yeah we must see the map
where is the map here is the map so
let's go to the map
and let's let's take a look at this all
right we must have the map maps are
essential to understanding geopolitics
so look we can see the the boundaries of
Moscow of I'm sorry of Russia
so Ukraine
is de facto NATO uh territory it's a
proxy war that's being fought by
multiple by by fighters of multiple
nationalities Against One Nation Russia
that's what's happening in the Ukraine
conflict uh Belarus you can say is is a
Russian state or Russian client State
the recently the Russians have
transferred nuclear weapons or maybe
they're in the process of transferring
nuclear weapons to to the soil of
Belarus but if you look at Estonia
Latvia Lithuania Finland Etc these are
all pro NATO very strongly proud NATO
Nations
um if you come to the South you have
turkey which is pronato and so on so
Russia from the West is essentially
encircled and the Americans have lots of
nuclear weapons deployed in various
parts of Europe they also have nuclear
submarines and so on
so if the Russians go crazy
hypothetically and launch you know
deploy nuclear I mean launch a nuclear
strike on Ukraine somewhere then there
will most likely be a retaliation from
the U.S which means from NATO and it
will happen from European territory see
Europe Western Europe is a huge buffer
zone for America it is something that
prevents the Russians from advancing
westwards that is the real utility of
Europe for the Americans so if there is
a nuclear war to be fought they will
they will launch the nuclear strikes
from Europe itself so that any response
will
hit Europe and not the U.S
okay so that's the utility of Europe it
will absorb it will be the buffer it
will absorb the brunt of Russia's
nuclear retaliation if it ever happens
so the retaliation will not be from the
from the U.S soil it would be from
Europe or from from Ukraine in case
Americans have any nukes there I'm sure
they I think they don't have any okay so
that's a deal first that's the first
part of the question secondly how would
the bharatiya government react
do a hypothetical Russian nuclear strike
on Ukraine
it will be a very strong condemnation of
Russia that's what India will do
India will have no choice but to condemn
Russia if Russia launches of you know an
unprovoked
or first strike on Ukraine if Russia
is hit by a nuclear strike and then
retaliates India will will not condemn
it but any Nation who launches a first
strike will get intense condemnation
what do they say in Hindi Hindi cutting
in the or something like that the the
harshest of condemnation that's what you
will get from India so if Russia does it
that's what India that's how India will
have no option but to respond India will
not announce a lockdown what do you do
with the lockdown
first of all there if there's a nuclear
strike somewhere there in Ukraine or
Russia it's not going to affect India
unless there are hundreds of nuclear
weapons being destroyed which is world
war three in which case it will affect
the entire world
so imagine you have a nuclear disaster
somewhere okay imagine you're in in some
place on the planet on the surface
you're just stay in some City and let's
say a hundred kilometers away there is a
nuclear explosion maybe a nuclear
reactor explodes or a nuclear strike
by announcing a lockdown what are you
gonna achieve
radiation doesn't care about walls
radiation flows through the air
all right so for that you have to
understand a little bit of physics so a
lockdown will do nothing
okay if there is radiation poisoning and
there's radiation in the air
a lockdown will achieve nothing so
there's nothing you can do about that
okay so that's I I think the answer to
the question India will condemn such an
action if it ever happens I don't think
it will happen
Amman said he says what can India learn
from the Russia Ukraine conflict how can
how how can India ensure that it rises
and get its lost territories back and
forth okay let's not talk about getting
lost territories in akhan Bharat and all
that stuff let's address the actual
question the first part of the question
what lessons can India learn from the
Ukraine Russia conflict
so the first thing the first lesson
India can learn is that you need
enormous stockpiles of ammunition you
need millions of bullets
you need a huge quantities of artillery
shells
you need very large numbers of missiles
tens of thousands of missiles
and uh that's that's number one you need
lots of that you need to have enormous
stockpiles of ammunition and bullets and
artillery shells and missiles cruise
missiles various kinds of missiles
enough to last years not three weeks or
four weeks or whatever
there's no guarantee any war will be
short and sharp Wars can be drawn out
worse long simmering conflicts look at
what's happening in Ukraine so you need
enormous stockpiles of ammunition and
missiles that's number one
secondly we have seen that the
um
we have seen not just in the Russia
Ukraine conflict but also in the uh
Azerbaijan Armenia conflict the
increasing and critical role that drones
you know loitering Munitions are are
playing very cheap
loitering Munitions and drones
quadcopters they are playing a critical
role in these battles and in this
conflict
so a drone a cheap drone can take out a
tank the Shahid drones can take out I
mean they can take out buildings and
whatnot
uh so yeah and and quadcopter you know
very uh very roughly very very quickly
modified rigged quadcopters can can take
out soldiers enemy soldiers in a very
pinpoint manner from the sky and you can
actually see the whole thing happening
terrible but that's how it is so
we cannot we can no longer fight 20th
century Wars anymore we have to uh
firmly come into the 21st century and
start utilizing 21st century technology
and you know the new technology the very
cheap disposable technology like drones
and all that it's making very expensive
weapon systems increasingly obsolete so
India cannot afford to be left behind
this
the Indian strategic planners and
thinkers and Generals Etc need to I'm
sure they're doing it and nobody to
lecture them I'm saying these are the
lessons that India needs to learn we
need to keep watching what's happening
in a sense from the Western perspective
Ukraine is like a laboratory where you
can see how the future of Wars will be
fought
yeah so so that's number two the
increasing and very relevant uh role
that drones and new technology unmanned
systems will play recently we saw this
video at this event in which a bunch of
Ukrainian uh remote controlled unmanned
boats
tried to take out a Russian warship I
think at least one of these boats was
able to Ram the warship that's what it
looks like from what we have seen
so if you have a boat which has no
Personnel on it it's a high speed boat
you either remote control it just like
you would do with a drone or you
equipped with with a with an AI system
and you put explosive explosives in that
then that's a very cheap
uh means of trying to destroy destroy a
warship I mean you can use a million
dollar missile like the I don't know how
much the brahmos costs per piece must be
close to a million dollars brahmos
missiles instead of that you use a fifty
thousand dollar boat
and you use 20 of those it's very hard
to take out 20. so you know that gives
you a higher chance a higher probability
of of taking out uh
of taking out the the warship so that's
another thing so there are a number of
these lessons to be
learned and thirdly Russia has been able
to withstand U.S sanctions
because it is an otaki what's an otaki
it's completely self-sufficient in in
all the critical resources completely
self-sufficient in agriculture
completely self-sufficient in petroleum
and oil and natural gas and coal and in
iron and all the essentials that it
takes to have a functioning economy and
a functioning Nation Russia is
completely self-sufficient in this and
and and that's why they have been able
to withstand the sanctions the sanctions
have done nothing more or less nothing
obviously the Russian Ruble has overall
you know withstood the sanctions very
robustly there's been some fluctuations
up and down but overall it's been able
to withstand these sanctions very
robustly and of course Russia has been
able to uh find Outlets
for its oil that it's no longer able to
supply to Europe because of all this so
it's it's found the outlets in China and
India mainly and other nations as well
so these are the things that allowed
that have enabled Russia to withstand
the sanctions to survive the sanctions
and so far it's doing well
so these are some of the lessons these
are some of the lessons I'm sure I can
think about this for a couple of hours
and list down on a whole lot more points
but this is what I can think of of the
top of my head there's so many lessons
that India needs to learn from this
anmol says the new U.S ambassador to
India Mr Eric Garcetti is showering
Praises on Prime Minister Modi his track
record would suggest otherwise your
thoughts on this my thoughts are very
clear words have no meaning like I keep
saying I'm sure there are lots of new
viewers here and welcome to all of you
like I keep saying words are meaningless
only actions matter
you can sweet talk as much as long as as
much as you want but if you're the the
words are meaningless if your actions
are the opposite of that I mean you're
stabbing somebody in the back of the
front with one hand and then sweet
talking them what what difference does
it make
um
so uh the words are meaningless in the
past Indian leaders were very
susceptible to flattery I will not take
names but the Americans had a very clear
policy that just flatter the Indian
leader whoever comes say very nice
things very complementary things about
them and their nation and then you will
you can get anything done from them so
that no longer works because
now India actually uh plays the real
geopolitical game words don't matter
anymore and that's and we have a very
clear and very very uh well articulated
and very well thought out foreign policy
the Modi Doctrine which is which is also
known as the Jai Shankar Doctrine will
understand that Mr jayashankar Dr Jai
Shankar is simply implementing the will
of Prime Minister Modi so it's actually
the Modi Doctrine so uh when it comes to
Mr Garcetti and
him showering Praises on Mr Modi well he
can keep doing that I'm I have nothing
against that but we need to examine his
actions he's a very newly minted
Ambassador and uh we have to Keynote on
him and see what actions he takes so in
the past the American uh Diplomat
station in India have tried to indulge
in what they call a sub-national
diplomacy which of course it's about
creating more Fishers and divisions than
India
uh
engaging with anti-india forces within
India and all that and Mr Garcetti like
like anmol says his track record we know
it very well he he is a Biden loyalist
he has been given this this
ambassadorship to India essentially as a
reward for services rented to Joe Biden
in in the the political party the
Democratic party and all that and his
track record is tells you that he is a
very
you know an extreme leftist they
destroyed the state of California or not
the state of California
um the city I think it was La wasn't it
Los Angeles that he was the mayor of he
presided over the ruin of the city
um so he is a very uh he's got a very
dubious and questionable track record
and obviously they have picked him and
sent him as ambassador to India to to
play a certain role so we need to keep a
very uh close watch from him I'm sure
the Indian government will do it and we
will do whatever we can to mitigate
whatever harm intends to cause in India
uh so let him shower as many Praises as
he wants on Mr Modi on India we must be
wise to these things we can no longer be
treated like little children it was so
easy to do just flatter India and you
know get things done get things done
that won't work anymore
Jay-Z says hello what's your opinion on
Bob Lazar is it is it true what he is
saying that he worked in Area 51 and he
was involved in reverse engineering
alien aircraft and so on alien craft
okay
so Bob laser is is is a guy who says
that he worked in Area 51 what is Area
51 shall you find out let's take a look
at the map let's let's discover area 51.
so Area 51 we need to go to the United
States for that all right we are in
United States I think it's in the state
of Nevada let's let's now search for it
area
51. Nevada
so this is what it looks like from above
as you can see it's a dry lake bed in
the middle of essentially nowhere the
Nevada desert
and it's it's kind of close off you try
to cross the boundary you're going to
get shot essentially by the by the uh
for the forces and as you can see
there's this enormously long Runway over
here very long let's try and measure the
length shall we measure the length from
from one end to another
measure the distance from here to there
it's almost eight kilometers it's it's
over eight kilometers so that's an
enormous Runway typically a Runway that
can accommodate very heavy aircraft
would be about two to three kilo maybe
three kilometers long
so this is enormous
now I'm not sure how functional it is
but there you have it so this is
essentially a testing facility where the
American Military and it's associated in
organizations they test experimental
futuristic aircraft and maybe spacecraft
it's essentially about testing
the next generation of Cutting Edge
military aircraft that's what it is okay
so this place is Area 51 and as you can
see they have many buildings and for all
these things over here
and there are hangers over here and we
cannot see what's inside clearly
obviously they will keep it concealed
and there are certain standard aircraft
that are sitting over here parked over
there
and so on so it's a testing facility
that's what Area 51 is now this uh
gentleman Bob laser claims that he
worked there that's that's the first
claim he has made and like like uh Jay-Z
is saying he says his claimed that uh he
worked on uh
reverse engineering alien
technology so what he is saying is that
in Area 51 the U.S government has at
least one if not many multiple alien
what we would colloquially call UFOs or
flying saucers so alien aircraft
alien craft spacecraft aircraft whatever
you want to call it they have a few of
those and they are reverse engineering
the technology of these uh Alien craft
that's what he has claimed and there are
also rumors or claims that they have
some you know alien
extraterrestrial beings who's who died
and whose bodies are preserved or kept
over there and so on
that's the claim that's been made so now
what can we say about what can I say
about this so from my perspective there
are two options there are two
possibilities there are two possible
scenarios one scenario is that Bob Lazar
is telling the truth the other scenario
is that he is lying and right now we're
in a superposition of these two
scenarios why are we in a superposition
that he may be
why is it so it's because we don't have
any evidence
see
if you make a claim
you have to present evidence to back up
your claim and if you make an
extraordinary claim you have to present
extraordinary evidence and the burden of
proof always lies on the person who
makes a claim
understand this
that's how it goes imagine you Bob laser
were to go to court
to court
and claim to the and claim in front of
the judge that so and so
happened that I I did so and so and
there are alien artifacts over there so
the judge will say show me the evidence
and if Bob laser is unable to provide
hard incontrovertible evidence he will
be thrown out of the Court
right it will not be accepted so that's
how it goes if somebody makes a claim
they have to present evidence now now I
understand that this is a top secret
facility and if you work there you will
not be allowed to take out any video
recordings any photograph even a square
centimeter of anything which is in there
so I understand that even if this were
true I understand why he would not have
any evidence
but unfortunately from my perspective I
can believe something only when I see
evidence in Sanskrit we call this
project
right
visible hard evidence
that is the best kind of evidence then
you have anuman and other other forms of
evidence which are inferior to
pratyaksha prama hard evidence empirical
evidence so when it comes to Bob laser
he may or may not be telling the truth I
do not know because I don't have any
evidence now I agree that I I myself
have said this that the absence of
evidence is not the evidence of absence
but it makes it
hard to believe a claim right so what
can I say about this what's my opinion
my opinion is that I do not know whether
it is telling the truth or whether he is
lying I don't know
I I'm sure it's possible
I mean the probability that he is
telling the truth may be on the lower
side but I you cannot rule out
the possibility that maybe the Americans
have something but then the question
obviously arises The Logical question is
why do aliens and UFOs only visit the US
why not any other Nation why haven't
they visited India or China or or other
other nations why do we never find
evidence actual proper high quality
video evidence 4K video evidence 1080p
video evidence that is incontrovertible
and why can't we find a single event
that's been witnessed by let's say 15
different people at the same time we now
find such such events you know so that's
why
it's kind of hard to believe this so uh
so my opinion is that I don't know I
think that the probability that he is
telling the truth is on the lower side
but I will not rule that out completely
but in the absence of evidence I can say
nothing about this
Jay says what is tabi's star and what's
the big
burning mystery about tabi star so tabi
star so this this is a very mysterious
star
that lies about roughly 1500 light years
from here from the earth what is a light
year it's a unit of distance light
travels at roughly three hundred
thousand three lakh
kilometers
per second is it kilometers is it meters
look it up it travels at an extremely
high speed okay light
so
the amount the distance
that light travels one year that's
called a light year okay it was not
kilometers it was meters okay so it's
300 000 meters per second that's the
speed of light roughly roughly give or
take so in one second light travels 300
000 meters multiply that by 60
by
by 330 365 that's the amount of light a
distance it travels in a year that's a
light year
so Tabby star is about 1500 roughly
light years from Earth that's number one
now this is one of standard main
sequence kind of star
but there is something extremely
mysterious about it and the Mystery has
not been resolved what's the mystery
so the mystery was brought to light by a
scientist uh by a graduate student PhD
student named
she was I think doing her PhD at the
time I'm sure now she has um
she's she's she must be uh teaching by
now
so her name is
the nickname is Tabby that's why it's
called tabi star so let me put something
on the screen and show you a very
technical scientific document but I'll
just show it to you briefly so that you
don't get confused
uh so this is where the Mystery Begins
this
uh research paper Planet Hunters X
whatever where's the flux
so big so after this paper was announced
and and published this star became you
know like a celebrity it became big news
and even beyond the scientific Community
it became big news it became big big on
the media so it's called the WTF star
where's the flux okay that's what
where's the flux actually means WTF so
it's either called the WTF star or
tabi's star
so here's the mystery
so
we we have discovered lots of exoplanets
right planets that are in orbit around
distant Stars one of the ways of
detecting an exoplanet is to uh you know
Point your telescope or your instrument
to detector at the star
and see if you you find certain dips in
brightness
so in case the orbit of an exoplanet is
directly aligned in the line in the
plane between us and that star then
momentarily the planet will come between
us and the star
while doing it's you know it's orbit
around around the star so when the
planet crosses when it transits the star
you will suddenly your detector your
instrument will suddenly witness and
record a dip in brightness
and these dips when stars go when
planets go around stars are periodic
let's say a planet goes around a star
once in 10 days then you will get a dip
in brightness once in every 10 days on
schedule
okay so that's how you detect one of the
ways of detecting exoplanets so this
star
had this kind of detective instrument
pointed at it at it and what was
detected was shocking
so instead of
uh you know regular
dips in brightness once in so many days
or once in so many months this star had
random dips in brightness random
lots of depth in brightness and some of
the dips were so drastic it was like 20
percent of the Starlight was being
occulted 20 percent up to 20 percent
roughly that's an enormous dip see even
if you have a Jupiter sized planet that
goes in front of the sun it's gonna you
know cause a decline in the brightness
by one or two percent at most 20 means
it's a massive object that is coming
between us and that star and these dips
in brightness were happening randomly
there was no set pattern which you will
have when there's something in orbit
around the star so that was the big
mystery and then several explanations
were were proposed
first of all they made sure that there
is nothing wrong with the
instrumentation and all that that was
that was done so there's nothing wrong
with the instrumentation the data is
real then how do you explain this so one
of the explanations is that there was
there is a massive swarm of comets
around the star and that these comets
are so numerous and so so so so you know
that's why it's we get this dips in
brightness and they're very random but
it doesn't sound very plausible I mean
how can you have a comment that that you
know Shades out 20 of the Starlight
that's weird secondly the promos they
propose that there must be a huge
Interstellar uh you know dust dust cloud
or something something like that
circumstellar dust dust cloud much
larger than what we have ever seen
anywhere else but once again
it doesn't quite make sense you know and
the third possibility that that got
everybody very hyped up including the
media is the possibility of a Dyson
Sphere
around the star so Dyson Sphere or a
Dyson structure is an artificial
structure that can only be constructed
by a very Advanced civilization Way
Beyond human capabilities
well let's let's uh let's Google it and
Dyson surface or whatever Dyson
Tyson sphere
and let's put that on the screen so that
you you understand what what we are
dealing with here
so it's named after Freeman Dyson who
first came up with this idea
so this is what a Dyson
sphere or our structure would look like
an alien megastructure so the purpose or
objective of such a structure would be
to harness The Starlight and and you
know convert that into energy so you
would need to have an extremely Advanced
non-human civilization to do this right
so then actually this is way more
plausible
then a swarm of comets or in a massive
circumstellar dust uh disc or whatever
right so so that is the mystery of tabe
star it looks I mean one of the
possibilities that's been considered
seriously is the possibility that there
is
an alien mega structure in orbit around
the star
you know so uh as of today the mystery
has not been resolved uh obviously we
would try to first look at non-alien and
non-extreme possibilities like the
possibility of
a huge swarm of comets or something like
that but it doesn't
kind of sound very plausible it doesn't
really explain the data that we have
so as of now we don't have an answer but
yeah the the alien megastructure angle
is still very much active so that and I
think they've discovered more than one
planet a star like this now
so yeah the mystery may be deepening
actually
but we still cannot say for sure that we
have discovered something specific like
in Alien megastructure but yeah it's
interesting
so that's why the media I think this was
discovered in 2017 2018 a few years ago
and there was a big media hype about
this for a while now it's kind of
receded into the background but the
mystery is still there so that's what
tab a star is and that's the mystery
surrounding it interesting
sahana says what's happening to Earth's
magnetic field why is it weakening are
the magnetic poles shifting what are the
consequences okay so the Earth has a
magnetic field
magnetic lines of force that come out of
the South Pole and re-enter the North
Pole
let's put an image on the screen so that
you get an idea
Earth magnetic field and let's put that
on the screen now let me explain why we
have a magnetic field as well and what's
happening with it
so what does Earth's magnetic field look
like it looks something like this okay
this is a better image maybe so if you
see this image you will see that the
Magnetic North and South poles are not
exactly aligned with the geographic
North and South Pole you go to the North
Pole of the earth you know exactly where
the geographic North Pole is there'll be
a marker there you go to Antarctica you
will know exactly whether the
geographical Geographic South Pole is
that you will find a marker there also
but the geographic North Pole does not
coincide with the Magnetic North Pole in
the geographic South Pole does not
coincide exactly with this magnetic
South Pole the magnetic poles keep on
moving over time so as you can see there
is a difference between these things now
what what creates the magnetic field
first of all let's address this Earth
internal structure
there you have it so if if you look here
the Earth the internal structure of the
earth is something like this you have
the crust which on on Whose surface will
live then you have the mantle the outer
core in the inner core the outer core is
molten metal mostly iron and nickel and
the inner core is solid metal it's
extremely hot why is it so hot
it's it's the heat that's left over from
the beginning the birth of the solar
system yeah
so the liquid outer core it keeps
flowing it keeps flowing and this
flowing and the other cause of the heat
is is radiation inside the earth so the
liquid outer core keeps flowing it has
currents
and the Earth also rotates and there we
have currents and you have precession
um and you have the Coriolis effect I'll
not go into that and all so that is what
causes
currents flowing because you have
charged particles in ions and all that
so you have currents flowing inside the
earth electric currents very powerful
electric currents that flow along with
the flowing of the of the molten metal
and these electrical currents when they
flow they create massive magnetic fields
and that's why the Earth has this big
magnetic fields and the North Pole in
the South Pole north magnetic poles and
South magnetic pole and this magnetic
field of the earth it protects us
without it we would not be alive
it protects us from solar radiation
it protects us from cosmic rays
so that's why the magnetic field is
essential for life and you know if the
magnetic field disappears then much of
the water will start evaporating very
fast and so on and so on like what
happened on Mars so that's why we have a
magnetic field in very very I'm giving
you a very rough idea of why now what's
happening what's happening is that the
magnetic field first of all is weakening
kind of uh and it's moving
so I believe right now the magnetic
field is is moving away from from
from wherever it the North Pole is
magnetic north is it's moving towards
Russia I think the speed is about 50
kilometers every year that's that's
significant
and similar something similarly
something is uh similar is happening
with the South magnetic pole as well so
the poles are slowly shifting now this
is a natural process it happens or the
last time the pool reversal also happens
you know so the last time you had a pole
reversal was nearly a million years ago
nearly I think 700 or 800
000 years before today or roughly a
million years before today and
and in between you have you know a
weakening of the magnetic field and all
these things so this is a natural
process it's a cyclical process it keeps
happening once in so many hundred
thousand years maybe roughly a million
years and you have you know the shifting
of the magnetic poles so what are the
consequences of this firstly if you have
a weaker magnetic field
then what will happen is that you will
have more cosmic rays and more of solar
radiation uh impinging the surface of
the Earth so that could perhaps possibly
or maybe definitely cause a higher
incidence of skin cancer and things like
that so that's one one consequence of
that
uh the weakening of the magnetic field
and uh when the magnetic field becomes
weaker there are these migratory animals
and birds especially birds that rely on
sensing the magnetic field they have the
Sixth Sense kind of you know they can
sense the magnetic field so if the
magnetic field becomes weaker than their
migratory patterns may be affected if
the poles shift in rivers then also you
may have some consequences that we may
not still understand yet we may not be
able to predict them so that's the deal
so that's what's happening it's a
natural phenomenon we cannot stop it if
it happens it happens when it happens it
will happen so the impulse some at some
point in time in the future will certain
certainly reverse
the
geographic North Pole will be the home
of this magnetic South Pole eventually
that's what's going to happen in the
future when I'm not sure when we don't
we don't quite know when it could happen
suddenly it could happen over time we
still don't understand very well because
we don't have sufficient data about the
internal structure of the earth we know
there is this liquid outer core liquid
metal but we don't know the the nature
of the currents and vortexes and all
that
so we cannot model that in the absence
of data that's why we don't know how how
fast this happens and when it will
happen so that's the deal that's what's
happening to the Earth's magnetic field
it is weakening that is a that's a
natural thing it happens when the poles
are moving away
um it may strengthen also in the future
depending on the conditions inside the
Earth
and I think we discussed some of the
consequences of this
Rock RV says could you please tell us
about the bodhyana Sutra controversy
so yeah interesting interesting the
bodhyana
is a Vedic text a late Vedic text why do
I say it's late Vedic because it's part
of the Krishna Veda the black YouTuber
which is the fourth
I think the third or the fourth which
video is it let me know in the comments
or in the live chat uh the Krishna Veda
okay so it's a late Vedic text and we
don't quite know when it was written
clearly more than two thousand years ago
most likely much before that but we
still don't have a very clear uh idea of
when The Vedic texts were written uh the
time frames and all that and I don't
want to get into the controversy at all
the dating and all that yeah so what's
the controller say about so first of all
let's talk about what the text is the
text refers to many things but one of
the passages in the text is D refers to
a Vedic King called amavaso
okay he was one of our ancient Kings
from the from the late Vedic period his
name was Amma also it is said in this
text that he migrated in a certain
direction and his people are the
gandhari the parsho and the Arata
so let's deal with that his people it
says at the gandhari the parshu and the
Arata so when we talk about the gandhari
or Gandara people if we understand who
they are they're the people of the far
north of India which is now presently
Afghanistan historically it's been part
of India and Indian civilization and
so on so
where it says his people are the
gandhari we know it's the people that
once lived in the present day
Afghanistan our people
who are the pursue
they are the people who live to the west
of India the parshoa people present-day
Persians they were once very closely
related to us even today they are
most likely Armenia the the region of
Mount Ararat or something so it talks
about a migration done by our Ancient
King amavasu it says his people are the
gandhari the parshut anata which is the
people of Afghanistan present day Persia
and most likely the the
Anatolia Armenia region it tells you
the geographical extent of his people
now the controversy was about the
direction of the migration which
direction did obamasu migrate in
and there's this professor you know this
German American Professor great scholar
great indologist or whatever
scholar who knows Sanskrit and he
translated this
this text
and in his translation
amavasu migrates eastwards
okay so Michael witzel translated as an
expert the text and his translation was
that amavasu migrated eastwards
eastwards
now before Michael Wiesel other Scholars
had also translated this text and they
all translated it to mean in such a way
that it their translation was that
migrated westwards but Michael witzel
said he migrated eastwards and then the
Indian wonderful historians like rubila
thapar and others they jumped upon this
new translation by Michael witzel and
they said this is proof
this is literally proof of an Aryan
invasion of migration into India
also was a Aryan invader
who came from gandhar
and came into India
and this proves the Aryan Invasion
migration tourism picnic Theory yeah
so uh romula thapar you know she he
jumped upon this and various other
Indian Court histories darbari
historians also started touting this
as the definitive literary evidence of
an Aryan
migration at least if not Invasion into
India now what happens is that Conrad
elst looked at this he is also a very
famous a Belgian indologist and he said
what are you talking about Michael
witzel
do you understand the ABCs of Sanskrit
this is referring to an a westward
migration
and then it's been proven Beyond doubt
that Michael witzel was fabricating the
evidence
the text the Sanskrit texts text clearly
unambiguously refers to a westward
migration of the king amavasu so what
actually the text is saying is that
amavasu in ancient Indian king migrated
to the West and his people are the
Gandara
this is referring to an out of India
migration westward migration
into Persia and essentially into
Anatolia do we know where Anatolia is
okay another opportunity for me to bring
out the map because I love the map
where's the map
here's the map
here it is
so it's referring to like I said
Gandhara means present-day Afghanistan
parshu means present-day Persia or Iran
and Arata is most likely
the Armenia Azerbaijan Georgia region
and Eastern Anatolia
so amavasu migrated all the way over
here
and there is a mount amasya in in this
region
you know so the names also kind of it's
not inclusive definitive evidence but
it's circumstantial evidence
so the controversy was about Michael
witzel this wonderful imminent
indologist who tried to fabricate
evidence of an Aryan migration into
India he was caught lying and he has
been exposed and yet he is still
thoroughly fitted and regarded as an
imminent indologist even today
even today
so it tells you that if you do something
if you if you indulge in this sort of
academic fraud
as long as you do it as long as it is
anti-india it works you will it will not
hurt your academic career yeah so that's
the kind of fabrication that Michael
witzel did
and they were here to he he paid no
price for that there were no no
consequences
so that's what the controversy was about
the both the Sutra controversy
all right next
swapnil says before the emergence of
spoken and written language how did
human beings communicate with each other
what led to the development of language
how long did it take for humans to reach
that stage in their history hashtag
anthropology so uh
the first question that would arise is
when did humans start speaking and we
don't have any evidence we don't have
any answer you ask any historian any
Anthropologist any any
archaeologist whatever we don't know
when the first language
appeared or this first speech appeared
the oldest language that we know of
today
is Vedic Sanskrit now I'm sure lots of
people will disagree here which is the
wrong blah blah blah blah blah that is
hittite or whatever they'll say but the
truth is
that the oldest language that we know of
is Vedic Sanskrit human language but
clearly that language came from an older
language because that's how it always
goes
and
anatomically modern humans have
they are we know that our species Homo
sapiens has existed for roughly 300 000
years three lakh years the oldest
evidence of homo sapiens anatomically
modern Homo sapiens is from jabel erud
in Northern Africa
and that's that evidence is about 300
000 years old
so if those
skeletons or bones artifacts remains
that were discovered represent
anatomically modern humans they would
have been able to speak just the way we
do and there is no
evidence that they were less intelligent
than us so let's assume that humans were
speaking three lakh years ago 300 000
years ago
but it doesn't mean this they suddenly
started speaking overnight
maybe they were speaking before that
maybe our Neanderthal cousins and
sisters some of them some of us may have
Neanderthal ancestors mostly Indians
don't have it but overall so maybe our
Neanderthal cousins Also may have been
able to speak we don't know
so there's nothing when you when you say
the human skeletal structure
there is nothing to suggest that there
is the capability for speech the ability
to speak
because the voice box is not a bone it's
not a bony structure it's it's cartilage
and other tissues
so uh looking at skeletal evidence you
can't really tell whether a certain
individual was capable of speech or not
so we don't know
when speech emerged and we don't know
how human beings
uh
communicated before so one of the
evidences we can look into how did
humans communicate before speech was a
thing because clearly Beyond a certain
time period I'm sure humans did not have
the ability to speak and there was no
language I mean look at our closest uh
primate cousins the chimpanzees the
gorillas the bonobos the orangutans the
ghibons
ETC they don't speak they don't have
speech
yeah
but they do communicate with each other
they do have vocalizations but they
don't have speech they have voices there
they can make sounds and all but they
don't have speech so the close our
closest related relatives are the
chimpanzees
and they are very close to us yes
including being very aggressive and
warlike
so how do chimpanzees communicate they
have very complex Communications they
have very complex social structures
hierarchical social structures
inequality oh my God oh my God they have
inequality what should we do about them
should we vocify them
so they communicate without speech look
at our second closest uh relatives
private relatives the gorillas they also
have very complex hierarchical societies
and they also have complex and
sophisticated communication despite not
being able to speak
so I am sure our ancestors pre-human
ancestors also would have communicated
in similar ways we have living examples
in front of us yeah now the question is
uh what led to the development of
language how long did it take for humans
to reach that stage in the history see
we don't have anything to compare with
because we don't have any any other uh
species of animal on the planet that has
this ability that we have uh we are the
only species
as far as we know in human in in the on
the Earth's history on the Earth's
history that has developed the ability
to speak so if we had another reference
point and we could study that then we
could tell but typically it takes this
much time for a species to develop the
ability to speak in our case we don't
know
so I don't know what happened and what
can only speculate as to what led to
this and how long it took so the best I
can tell you is that if we if we look at
our closest primate relatives the
gorillas and the chimpanzees you can see
that they can communicate reasonably
well and rather you know they can create
sophisticated complex societies even
cultures
based on non-verbal communication they
have sign language they have body
language uh there may be other things
associated with it right size and all
these things matter and they also have
vocalizations but non-speech
vocalizations and if you see you know
you can train gorillas and chimpanzees
to to do sign language and they can
actually
form sentences and and and uh and
communicate complex
thoughts including abstract thoughts
you know there was this gorilla Coco I
think her name was Coco it was a female
gorilla uh she left behind a message for
humans when she was on a death bed take
care of the of the earth and be kind and
things like that I mean that's almost
like that that's what a human being
would say you know
so even though they cannot speak like us
they have thoughts that are in some way
similar to ours
so that's what I can say we don't know
what led to the development of language
I think one of the factors that could
lead to the development of language is
increased cranial capacity means
increased intelligence
uh that's that's one thing
so I think maybe it would happen once
you reach a certain stage in in your
cranial development and you find other
species as well like dolphins and and
killer whales orcas
orcas are not actually whales they're
actually Dolphins the largest dolphin
species so orcas and regular Dolphins
they also have complex uh uh
communication abilities they they
vocalize they have songs and they have
they they almost it's almost like this
peak you know and even whales they have
veiled songs and whale Communications so
it's a very interesting and complex
topic
and we don't have the answers we don't
have the answers but yeah I'm sure
there's a interesting research happening
as we speak on this topic right now
rudrajit says we all know that
indianization of Southeast Asia happened
in a very peaceful Manner and Southeast
Asian people willingly adopted Indian
culture but why did they do it did they
consider Indian culture Superior just
like we consider Western culture
Superior and try to adopt it as much as
we can so today what's happening is that
people are kind of aching Western
culture in Eastern countries you you go
to you know towns and villages in Africa
and you take pictures of children and
they'll make this signs and symbols
which you know these hand signs and all
that which they don't even know what
that means but they're just trying to be
cool and and they're trying to ape what
uh what they see on on the small screen
or the big screen no Western people
doing that they have no idea what it
means but they just try to do that to
appear cool similarly if a culture is
made to look cool everybody wants to
emulate that and ape that so what's
happening in India right now especially
among the among the youngsters is that
blindly aping what they think looks cool
because they want to look cool
it's not that that culture is superior
but it has been made to look cool
uh now yeah so that's that point now why
did the Southeast Asian Nations peoples
uh
adopt Indian culture they did not adopt
Indian culture wholesale they absorbed
elements of Indian culture and practices
into their own way of life
so what we see today let's say in
Cambodia or Vietnam or Indonesia Etc
Thailand Burma Laos
all that we see a syncretic culture
take the example of Japan let's take an
extreme example to the extreme East okay
let's go to the map so that we know what
we're talking about
so we have India which is the what
dominates Asia overall you go eastwards
you have Burma Thailand Laos Cambodia
Vietnam then you have China yeah the
Philippines South you have Malaysia
Indonesia all that then you have the
koreas and then you have Japan in the
very extreme east of Asia now Japan has
a very indianized culture whether we
realize it or not
uh
they have this and their culture is a
beautiful example of syncretic culture
they have their own
indigenous Shinto
culture their own system of Kami you
know deities and gods and goddesses and
spirits and all that and that has
syncretized with Indian culture and if
you ask any historian they'll say it is
Shinto syncretized with Buddhism well
that doesn't quite explain it because
every single Indian Hindu god and
goddess
has a place in Japan and they all have
Japanese names like benziteen and
what are the names all right
so what we find in Japan is syncretic
culture Shinto
syncretized with Hinduism Buddhism with
Indian culture similarly that's what
happened throughout Eastern Asia if you
go to Burma Myanmar today it's what's
called about Buddhist country you go to
Thailand today it's what's called about
this country but they have very
distinctive
a very distinctive way of being Buddhist
or Hindu I mean they they worship all
the Hindu gods like Lord Shiva and Lord
Ganesh Etc in Thailand you will find it
everywhere but its portrait is Buddhism
but it also has very distinctive Thai
elements so what happened is the
question so uh the indianization of
Southeast Asia began maybe 3000 or so
years ago it began with the Voyages of
merchants from Eastern India to these
places which part of western India
Kalinga now known as odisha odisha so it
began with the journeys of merchants
from odisha across
the the ocean Indian Ocean
and they started trading with Southeast
Asia
and that's how the first Contact
happened eventually you had these the
the foundation of various indianized
kingdoms like the funan Kingdom and
other kingdoms all across Southeast Asia
and we know there was no violence there
was no military conquest until a
thousand years ago the Chola Conquest
but that comes very much later in the
day so why did they adopt lots of
elements of Indian culture I mean
eventually all of Southeast Asia was
Hindu then it became known as Buddhist I
mean Angkor Wat is a Hindu temple the
largest Hindu temple that we know of in
the world Indonesia was entire Hindu the
majapahit uh phase of Indonesian history
is their Golden Era the Philippines were
a Hindu region and so on
how did this happen it Hinduism never
spread through force it spreads through
diffusion slow
diffusion so
maybe it is possible that they may have
considered Indian culture Superior
because Indians had this technology they
could travel vast distances on on ships
the Indians had huge ships very
sophisticated trips and maybe Indians
from of that time unlike today's Indians
were much more cultured and refined when
and better behaved perhaps our ancestors
right
and so overall they must have appeared
very cultured very refined very Superior
in some ways you know very well behaved
very kind and maybe this made an
impression over centuries and maybe it's
that people started trying to emulate
that and obviously when you're wealthy
people want to emulate that your Customs
the main reason why everybody wants to
ape the Westerly is because the West is
so prosperous they have acquired a in no
all the way of the world in the past 500
years and they and when you have
so much wealth and everything is well
organized you obviously appear Superior
and people want to try to emulate you
so India was that in the past
India accounted for
2000 years ago Angus Madison's research
tells us that India accounted for at
least a third of the world's GDP and
actually it most likely accounted for
more so maybe 3000 years ago India would
have accounted for half the world's GDP
it's very possible
so when you are that rich that
prosperous you have high technology and
you are so cultured and refined and
civilized and kind and compassionate and
all that and when you when you have Fair
Trade Practices and all those things in
unlike the the mandatory that the the
British
indulgent then people want to be like
you so I think that was the reason why
all these nations slowly over time
started absorbing Indian culture and
that's how the entirety of Southeast
Asia was Indian as China was indianized
Japan was indianized everything was
indianized and then in the past 1000
years because India fell so drastically
because of uh foreign occupation that's
why Indian influence slowly faded away
and we still have it even and still many
of these nations still have a lot of
Indian influence
geopolitical Dubey says the U.S is
still a military and economic superpower
but in the development of hypersonic
missiles why is the U.S behind China and
Russia why is the U.S unable to test
test Hypersonic missiles successfully
and why or how is China leading in this
weapons War interesting question so uh
the Americans actually
uh tested the concept of hypersonic
technology and they probably developed
some form of hypersonic technology in
the 1950s itself
1950s
but then they abandoned the development
of this technology because they thought
it had no use who needs missiles and
Rockets that travels so fast who needs
that what's the point so they abandoned
the development of this technology at
some point in time
then in the late
in the in the by the end of the 20th
century in the beginning of the 21st
century I think that the Russians and
the Chinese started uh uh researching
doing r d research and development of
hypersonic technology and today you have
a bunch of Russian and Chinese
Hypersonic missiles that essentially are
believed to believe to outperform
anything the U.S has so for instance we
have seen in the Ukraine conflict like a
couple of weeks ago it's it's happening
as you speak most likely the Russians
are are using this kinjal missile it's
an air launched missile that travels at
Mark 10 4.5 kilometers per second
roughly imagine a missile that that
flies four and a half kilometers every
second
it's an air launched missile the kinjal
and the ukrainians and NATO have no
response to it they are in no position
to shoot down the result they have made
claims okay in recent weeks that they
shot down a couple of King a few kinjal
missiles that was a joke that's a
complete fabrication and see the
evidence they are presenting yeah makes
no sense so uh the kinjal is a
Unstoppable Unstoppable missile right
now it travels 4.5 kilometers every
second it's an air launch missile the
Russians also have the Silicon missile
it's an anti-ship missile that travels
approximately three kilometers per
second it's Mark nine the Chinese of the
dong Feng missiles donken 17 dongfing 41
dong fing 27 I think the 17 in the in
the in the 40s 41 have uh Hypersonic
Glide vehicles hgvs at the tip you know
so these are icbms or irbms
InterContinental or intermediate
ballistic missiles intermediate range
palacing missiles which are equipped
with hypersonic Glide Vehicles so the
Chinese and the Russians have
somersaulted the Americans in the
development of hypersonic technology
the Americans are now trying to catch up
with this you know the Americans have
this long range Hypersonic weapon that
they are testing and they're developing
right now it's supposed to be you know
operational this year or something we
don't know what quite we don't quite
know what the status is they had the
agm-183 or something which failed that
was uh
through the project that they're working
on I think it failed it was canceled
they had various Hypersonic air
breathing weapons and they had
Hypersonic attack cruise missiles I
don't know what they exact they had
something called SCI fire
so the Americans were developing a were
working on a number of hypersonic uh
programs
trying to play catch up with Russia and
China we don't quite know what the
situation is but the Americans were the
pioneers of the technology I think they
first tried it out or tested it in the
1950s so there is no reason why they
cannot in the next couple of years you
know catch up with the Chinese my
question is what is India doing
we have the brahmos which is a
supersonic missile Mach 2 Mac 2 is
nothing compared to Mach 9 and Mach 10.
so India needs to not be left behind and
this is one of the lessons of the
Ukraine war right so that's the deal so
the Americans kind of were complacent
and that's why they fell behind now
they're trying to catch up as fast as
possible they have the
they have the means to do this they have
the the the experts and they have the
military industrial complex that can get
this done
so it's essentially for the U.S a
question of time
about when they catch up with the
Russians and the Chinese or maybe they
may have already done that and they may
have not announced it yeah so that is
the deal
I says we humans have nuclear submarines
nuclear aircraft carriers but why no
nuclear space Rockets we can go much
faster and further into space with these
Rockets why is no country work why why
does no country have working nuclear
Rockets until now well do you know
the
nuclear see one of the reasons why we
don't use
mostly nuclear propulsion
in missiles and Rockets is because when
the Mis let's say let's talk about
missiles first
a missile is designed to crash right and
destroy the target if you have nuclear
propulsion it's gonna
cause
nuclear pollution nuclear fallout
so that's that's something nobody wants
and yet the Russians have
such a missile so the Russians had
announced I think in 2018 or 2019 I
think 2018 a
nuclear-powered cruise missile let's
let's put that on the screen
check it out
Russia reveals Unstoppable
nuclear-powered cruise missile what it
means is that this missile has nuclear
propulsion
most missiles if not all
have chemical Rockets chemical
propulsion but this missile has nuclear
propulsion it is essentially it
essentially has unlimited range
so this has been done let me show you
something else so it is definitely
possible to uh you know have a rocket
that's powered by
nukes so this is something that the
Americans did you know try out here's
the here's a documentary about this to
Mars by A-bomb the secret history of
project Orion top scientists wanted to
build a nuclear bomb powered spaceship
to visit Mars and the planets and people
like Arthur C Clarke and Freeman Dyson
were involved in this project
and it actually works the concept works
so it can be done we already have a
nuclear-powered cruise missile
and we can have nuclear bomb powered
Rockets So essentially these Rockets
will be extremely large extremely
massive and there will be
powered by what what we could regard as
tactical nuclear warheads so you explore
the technical nuclear water it will it
will impel the rocket upwards then you
explode one more then one more then one
more that's what you do it you will but
that will cause a lot of radioactive
fallout you know as long as the rocket
is in the Earth's atmosphere but yeah it
certainly works it it the concept is
very feasible nobody has actually made
it so this this thing that I showed you
to Mars by a bomb they tried this out
with conventional explosives and it
works but they're not actually use the
larger scale version with nuclear
explosives but it can certainly work the
only reason so there are a couple of
reasons why people may not have done
this first of all it's very expensive
you don't want to use up your nuclear
warheads for this kind of thing
and secondly it can it will cause
radioactive fallout when you explode a
nuclear weapon it's going to release
radioactive material into the atmosphere
so that is radioactive pollution
radioactive fallout and that is
something nobody wants thirdly if
something goes wrong and the rocket
crashes all that nuclear fuel Etc will
be spilled
either on the ground or in the
atmosphere and that's again a
radiological disaster so these are the
reasons why it has never really been
done what the Russians have a nuclear
powered cruise missile and this sort of
large-scale nuclear propelled rocket can
certainly be built and the the
technology more or less exists for doing
that
okay two questions Mazar Chacha says
what are the key factors behind the
recent clashes between Afghanistan and
Iran along their shared border and how
might these incidents impact their
bilateral relations moving forward and
ronak says there's recent news about the
Taliban fighting against the Iran
military how does Iran perceive the
Taliban what's the conflict between Iran
and Taliban all about okay interesting
question
it's about water
let's take a look at the Geography okay
let's take a look at the geography
let's put the map on the screen as
always
here is the map let's remove this thing
over here so we're in our own
neighborhood Afghanistan Iran
now there is
a very famous river in Afghanistan
this is the Farah River I'm looking for
another one
is it
whichever is it this one
the hetu month
is the hanut
which river am I looking at
this is the hellmann
this is the river behind the entire
matter
so today this river is called the hell
month
in the past let's say two thousand years
ago it was called The hetumanth River
and even before that it was called the
sidhu month river in Sanskrit it means a
river on which there is a dam or a
bridge a dam most likely so in the
ancient days when Afghanistan was still
gandhar our ancestors had damned this
River and they called it the sethu band
or setup River eventually it came to be
known as the hetu month and now it's
called the hill month so this River
it flows in through most of Afghanistan
but then it drains into what was once a
lake here in Iran
I don't remember the name of this Lake
and if you look at the satellite imagery
there's no Lake here anymore the bus 20
or 30 years this lake has been dry this
Lake received its water from the from
the Helmand river which is which passes
through Afghanistan which is controlled
by Afghanistan and Afghanistan has dams
on this River
so Iran wants Afghanistan to release
sufficient water
into sistan Balochistan of Iran so that
this region can be irrigated and there's
there's a there's an agreement I think
it dates back to 1973 or something
between Afghanistan and Iran which
stipulates that Afghanistan must release
a certain amount of water
into Iran
while retaining the ability to you know
build dams and all that on the river so
the Iranian government is saying that
the Afghans are not releasing they're
not abiding by the agreement and they
are not releasing the amount of water
they are supposed to into Iran and which
is why the the lake has dried out and
there's essentially been this has turned
into a desert and so that's that's a
dispute it's a water dispute and I think
in 2021 or something the
uh a new dam was built a new dam I think
it was it's called the Kamal Khan Dam or
something the Afghans built a new dam
there and that's again one of the issues
that is called something that's that's
uh exacerbated the issue
now uh so that's what is causing the
current tensions between uh Iran and the
Afghanistan government the Taliban
government so let's take a look at some
images that the Taliban tweeted out yeah
so there is this funny account it's
called the Taliban public relations
department commentary
it's on Twitter
now it's clearly not an official account
of the Taliban and it's kind of a
humorous account it's not I would not
regard this exactly as a parody account
because the pictures that they post
nobody else has these pictures which
means it is being done from within the
Afghan government but the tone is very
humorous kind of
so check this out the Iran this is from
May 22 today is May 27th the Iranian
delegation met with our minister of
water and agriculture to discuss the
Water Crisis the discussion became
heated after a member of the Iranian
delegation insulted the minister our
heroic Minister threatened him with
flogging if he did not calm down so you
can see that they are adopting a
humorous Stone but this is a real event
and these pictures are not to be found
anywhere else
let's see this
this afternoon our masculine border
guards met with their Iranian
counterparts across our joint border as
both sides approached the border the
Iran General casually stepped over the
line to stay to shake hands and he was
quickly captured we treat border
violations very seriously you can see
this image it is an Iranian General
whose hands are tied Beyond his behind
his back he is being held by the Taliban
Personnel it's a very real image but the
tone of the Tweet is kind of serious
kind of kind of funny slightly slightly
humorous you know dark humor kind of
thing and this was tweeted on May 23
right is there anything else yeah one
more
this is May 24th
our foreign minister had a visit from
the Chinese Ambassador this morning he
has offered to resolve the water dispute
with Iran and is scheduled to fly to
Tehran this afternoon our message to the
Iranians is stiff and straight calm down
brothers so there is something Brewing
here this may or may not be an official
or unofficial Taliban account but what
they are tweeting is very real
and these images you will not find
anywhere else
so that's one thing so that is one
source that we can look at something is
brewing the the situation is not very
very happy very very calm there are
tensions On the Border let's see another
one this is an Iranian Twitter account
Iran International English
the Iranian president's warning to Kabul
over Iran's water share from the
hiramand okay they call it the hirmond
river has been mocked by a famous member
of Taliban known as general mobin who is
seen in this video offering president
raisy a gallon of water from the river
take this and don't attack us we are
terrified so in this video the Taliban
guy takes a yellow gallon container of
water from the river
and he offers it to Iran says please
don't attack us we are terrified of you
you know what this signifies
the Taliban suicide bombers are Infamous
for wearing yellow jackets or yellow
something
so it is
this this video it serves to mock the
Iranians make fun of them and also it
implicitly threatens them
that's what this is that is the
significance of this yellow
bucket or container or whatever it is
it's it's an implied threat to Iran so
as you can see relations are not good
between Iran and Afghanistan
there are there is tension Brewing
between these two Nations it's about
water the Iranians are demanding that
the Afghans release more water the
Afghans are saying that there is drought
what it's not raining and we don't have
enough water then that's why your lake
is drying out the Iranians are saying we
are not stupid
we have scientists we we have
meteorologists we know what's happening
you are deliberately withholding water
from us our Fair fear of water that is
what's happening it's a water dispute
and the Taliban seems to be very
confident they are kind of mocking the
Iranians
uh so as you can see Iran and
Afghanistan are not quite getting the
law
that's a deal
how does Iran perceive the Taliban I
expect that the the Iranians are happier
with the Taliban than the previous
regime which was a U.S puppet regime but
they still seem to consider the Taliban
to be kind of a nuisance that seems to
be the kind of uh thing there is you
know and and recently president raisy of
Iran of Iran had kind of threatened the
Taliban had he had used what we could
call robust language
uh with respect to this this crisis in
the Iranians are retali the Taliban are
retaliating in in this mocking fashion
so that's the interesting situation that
we are seeing
the developments between Iran and
Afghanistan
okay let's see how many more questions
we can take
saurabh says what is the Zen Zen Avista
when was it composed is it contemporary
with The Vedas
uh there why are there priests known as
Earth
priests are not called or whatever this
is they are called
a
thrawn or something let me go to the
encyclopedia iranica and show it to you
what what
their priests are called just give me a
second
as well
so yeah this is it
ravan
the this symbol over here that you see
on the screen is the Theta the Greek
Theta Theta Theta so this is pronounced
as
so that's the pronunciation that's
that's what they called their priests
the Zoro ocean priests so what was the
Zend avasta it was their holy text this
holy text holiest text whatever you want
to call it uh
and how old is it it's it's maybe 3000
years old maybe three and a half
thousand years old we don't quite know
when zarathustra lived so because you
know all
the records of Iran's history were
destroyed
after or during the Arabian Arabic
invasion of Iran some
13 1400 years ago so all the texts were
destroyed so we don't know when
zarathustra actually lived let's say
three eight thousand or 3500 500 years
ago roughly maybe perhaps so in that
case that's how old this end of esta is
it is there the holy text or the holiest
text of the zoroastrian religion and it
has a section called the gathas which is
a term we all understand in India as
well gatha means Katha stories which
deals with his life the life of
so that's what it was was it
contemporary with The Vedas I don't
think so it most likely came after The
Vedas
uh so that's what it is the priests were
called and is there any connection with
them maybe maybe see India and Persia
were Persia wasn't was a daughter
civilization of India and today the
persons many persons look very different
from Indians don't they
there are many persons who look almost
like Europeans
you will find a certain small percentage
of Persians Iranians who have blue or
green eyes and blonde hair and skin that
looks like you know the skin of
Europeans white skin
that's not how the original Iranians
looked the original Iranians had loud
light brown skin dark eyes and dark hair
they would kind of kind of look like me
kind of I know but why do Iranians look
so why do some Iranians look very
different today
it's because when the turkic
you know nadarsha who invaded India and
slaughtered a hundred thousand people in
one day in Delhi he was the king of Iran
right he was a Turk so his dynasty
his father and him and that time period
That's when lots of individuals were
settled in Iran from the Caucasus region
let me show you the Caucasus region in
case um
in case we need to look at that where's
the map okay here's the map
so the the Caucasus region is the kavkas
region it's the region between the Black
Sea and the Caspian Sea
the Azerbaijan Armenia Georgia region
Dagestan chechnya all that which is now
part of Russia that's north of Iran Iran
regards that as greater Iran but the
people who live there
in the Caucasus region ethnically they
are not Persians
they are most likely the descendants of
maybe ancient scitians one of the
languages spoken in this region is
called the Iran language which in the
ocean language is also spoken there
these languages are offshoots of the
ancient extinct scitian language
originally were Indian by the way that's
a whole different story will not go
there but uh the region of the Caucasus
region the people are ethnically
essentially they are European you know
the Caucasian so-called race it was
named after the people who lived in this
region who live in this region
the original Iranians looked like the
people of Afghanistan and Western India
today you have a complete mixing of
people so there are lots of Iranians who
have turkic ancestry now azerbaijani
ancestry and there are lots of Iranians
who have
the ancestry of the people of Caucasus
that's why Iran is kind of a mixed race
population today but ancient Iran looked
very different I mean you still have
people who look like the ancient
Iranians today in Iran but that's that's
the thing so uh coming back to the same
the Vista it was most likely most
probably written after The Vedas
and yeah there obviously could be some
connection with the other movie then the
words are very similar because the old
Persian language was like an upper bunch
of version of Sanskrit it was like a
brunch dialect dialect of Sanskrit it
was like like a practice language that's
what it was
wise man one two three four says my
question is USA is trying to regime
change okay the US is trying to
instigate or engineer a regime change
operation in Bangladesh
is it
for India or to check on China okay so
what evidence do we have of this let's
let's uh
honey blinken let's take a look at
Anthony blinken's Twitter account who is
and then Anthony blinken he is the
Secretary of State
of the United States what that means is
that he is their foreign minister okay
let's let's find his Twitter account
where is this guy
here he is
this is his Twitter account
so
May 24 he tweets this he says
today I announced a new Visa policy to
promote free and fair elections full
stop
under this policy we can impose visa
restrictions on individuals and their
immediate family members
if they are responsible for or complicit
in undermining the democratic election
process in Bangladesh
my question to the United States is
what business do you have interfering in
the Democratic electoral process of a
Sovereign Nation
who appointed you to be the moral
Guardians of the world
but that's what they do because they
have the force they have the powers they
feel they can do anything so essential
and you will see other tweets by
Americans and and Western people who are
accusing uh
uh what's the lady Sheikh Hasina
of being a dictator
so the thing is she has been winning
elections
and they don't like it
the thing why do they not like her is
it's because she has a pro-india policy
under her leadership under her
government relations between India and
Bangladesh have improved significantly
so that is something the Americans are
not happy about
they if you look at the past
78 years of of History the Americans
have always sought to destabilize India
they financed and funded Pakistani
terrorism and other activities against
India for decades the Americans did that
now Pakistan is a spent Force Pakistan
is nothing much more than nuisance value
for us
so they want to create new friends
one is Bangladesh so as long as this
lady Sheikh Hasina is in power in
Bangladesh we're gonna have stable and
good relations overall with Bangladesh
but if an anti-india Force like
khalidaziya comes to power then they can
use that so if they if they engineer an
election thing and bring this person
khalidaziya to power then she will be
beholden to them she will be essentially
their vasal their puppet and they can
and they will give her some benefits you
know good money or whatever it is then
they can use her in her government to
create such a certain situations and all
that on India's eastern flank and it's
very critical because a significant
portion of what we call the northeast of
India which is actually the Far East of
India is aborted by Bangladesh let's
take a look at the map
in case your geography syllabus did not
cover this
tripura mizoram
uh meghalaya all of this in Assam of
course you know so you can create lots
of trouble lots of problems in India's
Far East if you have
an anti-india government in Bangladesh
Now understand this the US does not want
India to rise too much it seeks to help
India in certain in certain ways as long
as it serves their objective of
containing China but it also seeks to
counter India and to hamper India's rise
in a whole lot of different areas
so that's the kind of policy dual policy
that the Americans have vis-a-vis India
they are now beginning to see India as a
potential long-term competitor and they
don't want to make the same mistake they
did with China they aided in updated
China's rise they've midwifed China's
rise to almost
you know superpower invading status
they don't want to make the same mistake
with India so they want to encircle
India create regime change operations
maybe in Nepal maybe in Bangladesh they
already have Pakistan on their side and
you know create trouble all around keep
India off balance at all times and and
ideally they would want a new government
in the different government in India in
2024. so that's the kind of game the
Americans are playing
so this has nothing to do with China
this is
targeted at India squarely at India and
it's becoming clear that the Americans
want a regime change in Bangladesh now
big big trouble if that happens for
India you know
okay samartha says how does
turkey View
and why is Ataturk shown as Turkish
Gandhi
and was Kamal more pro-us and pro-nato
who is better from India's perspective
firstly died in 1938.
NATO was formed in 1952
so there's no question of
being pronato because NATO did not even
exist even as an idea
at the time that Ataturk died 1938.
so Ataturk was not pronato NATO never
existed that's number one number two was
Ataturk pro-us no he was not pro us
he liberated his country from Western
occupiers in 1923. there was a two three
year
Turkish war of independence at the end
of the first World War
see what happened in World War one is
that turkey took the side of Germany and
Germany and the German accent the the
powers allied with Germany they lost
so turkey also lost and turkey was
partitioned it was balkanized
some parts of Turkey were given to some
European power another one to another
power that sort of thing happened so
turkey was like chopped up and and
parceled out to various Western powers
and it's in this situation that the
great military General perhaps the
greatest military General General the
Turks have seen in several centuries
he stepped into the into The Fray he
started a guerrilla war from this remote
stronghold in Anatolia called Ankara
which is now the capital he fought not
only the Western occupying Powers he
fought his own
ottoman Sultan the last Khalif
and he defeated them all he ousted them
all from turkey and he created a
Sovereign Nation of Turkey
so he fought the West multiple times
he he foiled Winston Churchill's 1915 I
think it was a year that the plan to
take the Dardanelles the Gully poly
Invasion it was one man who defeated the
West it was Mustafa Kemal Ataturk who
was then an unknown
uh you know military commander
so uh he spent his time his life his
military career fighting the West
and the US is part of the west but after
he was able to liberate turkey and
transform it into a Sovereign Nation he
embarked upon a process of
westernization
what he did is that he secularized he
forcibly secularized turkey imagine
the strength of will it would have taken
to take a nation like turkey and
secularize thoroughly
he banned the hijab and the parda and
the burka and all that for women
he banned the participation of of
religious Islamic clergy in the
government
he
he emancipated women he gave them equal
rights as men that was unthinkable
you know
and he he tried his best to modernize
turkey and within his lifetime by the
time he died turkey was a totally
transformation he he banned the Arabic
and the Persian script you know the the
right to left script he said that that
we don't have our own script but we will
use the a modified version of the Latin
script to write the Turkish language
we'll no longer use the Arabic of the
Persian script
so he totally transformed turkey one man
threw sheer force of will did this
and he died in 1938. now a certain
section of Turkish Society Society was
left behind in this process overall over
time he wanted the entirety of the
Turkish Nation to embrace this change
but the a certain section was left
behind which was the deeply conservative
people
and they are the ones who never liked
who who have not
and when it comes to
Richard erdogan he comes from that
background
so
if you look at his political party which
came to power in 2002 to 2003 somewhere
around there
they have never
extolled the virtues of Mustafa Kemal
Ataturk
erdogan until recently never even took
the name of Ataturk the word is a title
it means father of the Turks
it's not an actual surname
also did made this happen he insisted he
mandated that every Turkish person must
have a surname historically
traditionally the Turks did not have
surnames they only had first names
so his name was Mustafa
then his teacher because he was great at
mathematics gave him the name Kamal
which means excellent in Arabic so he
became Mustafa Kemal and after he
mandated that every Dirk should have a
surname the people of turkey insisted
that Mustafa Kemal should take the
surname Ataturk which means father of
Turks and he accepted
so uh that's how he got this name so
erdogan until very recently did not even
utter the word the name Ataturk from his
mouth so they don't like him
the the his political party doesn't like
him erdogan's entire political plank is
going back to traditional
ottoman values and going back to to
being an Islamic Nation
and the entire focus of Ataturk was the
opposite to abolish the caliphate
to move past the ottoman era
and to he tried to move past Islam as
well that's what Ataturk did
he tried to genuinely secularize the
nation
so erdogan is trying to take the nation
in the in exactly the opposite direction
so so erdogan does not like Ataturk his
political movement is anti-atark but
just like India's politicians have to
kind of pay lip service or more to Mr
Gandhi similarly
in Turkey you know they they are forced
to not be harshly critical or or even
slightly critical of they are forced to
to recognize him as the father of the
nation
but Kamal Ataturk cannot be regardless
as Turkish Gandhi
[Music]
Independence and sovereignty for his
country through through Force he forced
the occupiers out of turkey he booted
them out through military force and then
he transformed turkey according to his
vision
Mr Gandhi did the exact opposite of that
I'll not go into that right now so it is
completely incorrect to even compare
with Mohandas Gandhi I could do a
comparison video about that and I think
it will be
I wonder what comments I'll get when I
do that if I do that
all right all right all right
swarup says Germany has officially
entered into a recession what would be
the outcome of this for India How likely
is India to enter a recession because
India has zero percent likelihood of
entering a recession look at any
economic Financial uh you know analysis
of all the nations India is the only
nation that has a zero percent chance of
entering a recession India is the only
bright spot in the global economy India
is going to keep on growing as an
economy for the next two three decades
minimum as long as we have the right
leadership it's gonna keep growing well
is the India is the only nation
that has a chance of surpassing the
United States as the world's largest
economy in this Century that's like 30
40 years from now perhaps maybe 30
perhaps okay I'm not making any any
projection of a time frame so India has
no chance of entering a recession
Germany has now officially entered a
recession its GDP growth is negative
what does this mean for India overall
Germany is the economic engine that has
powered Western Europe and if Germany
enters a recession it's gonna you know
be bad for the entirety of Europe when a
nation is in recession
it's it becomes it can its people become
financially conservative they stop
spending so much they start saving they
stop consuming
no extra expenditure no going out for to
a restaurant twice a week or once a week
no splurging on entertainment we will
not watch three movies this month we'll
watch only one movie or maybe no movies
so cut down on your expenditure will not
buy any luxury items will not buy that
new laptop or new iPhone or whatever it
is right when this happens
the Nations that export such products
face problems because there are fewer
buyers of these things so when it comes
to make in India we want to manufacture
stuff in India and we want to export it
to the world we want to replace China as
the world's manufacturing Harbor right
so if the rest of the world is entering
a recession
I'm not saying the whole world is right
now it's Germany but you know recession
is like a disease it kind of spreads
it's kind of contagious
so it it could slow down to some extent
India's economic growth as well which is
why recession in any part of the world
is not good for the rest of the world
so uh overall
India should be careful India should
keep a very close eye on this of on
what's happening in Europe there is the
Ukraine war that's happening which has
been precipitated by Relentless NATO
expansion eastwards Russia were left
with no choice but to do this otherwise
they would be in like you know
existential crisis for them uh but now
the Americans have blown up that whoever
I mean whoever has blown it up has blown
it up the node stream to pipeline so
that cheap plentiful gas that was
driving Russian gas but cheap plentiful
Russian gas that was driving the
economic engine of Europe has now dried
out dried up now the Europeans have are
being forced to import gas from the
United States at three times the price
that is going to destroy your economy
and that's what's happening now
so uh German Germany's economy is going
and decline it's in recession now I hope
other nations don't follow suit but yeah
if there is recession in Europe if this
contagion spreads in the whole of Europe
goes into recession America's economy is
also not doing well if this happens it's
not good for India you know so that's
the thing it means that it will end up
slowing down India's economic growth as
well
so unless you're a nation that exports
raw materials
if if you're a nation that exports
oil and gas and coal and iron ore and
stuff like that then you can keep on
doing this even then a recession can can
hamper your output but if you're
exporting finished products that it's
going to hurt you a little bit more
maybe a lot more
so overall it's it's concerning for
India that's what I would say
saurabh says what's the
okay the Egyptian the Iranian the
Mesopotamian scripts and the Harappan
script
the former three scripts were deciphered
but why has the latter one not been
discussed the later later one not been
deciphered okay so the Egyptian script
has been deciphered the the Iranian or
Persian CUNY form script has been
deciphered the Mesopotamians cuneiform
script has been deciphered but why has
the Harappan script not been deciphered
that's the question so how was the the
Egyptian hieroglyphic script deciphered
it was deciphered through the fortuitous
discovery of the Rosetta Stone which had
the same inscription in three different
scripts and I think one of the scripts
was known so that's how they were able
to decipher the other one and that's how
the Egyptian hieroglyphic script was
deciphered how was the Iranian Persian
cuneiform script deciphered so for a
long time it stumped everybody they had
no clue as to how to decipher the script
then somebody hit upon a bright idea
what if the old Persian language was
similar to Sanskrit let's assume it is
sanskrit and let's try to make sense of
this once they made this assumption it
started falling into place because the
old Persian language was essentially an
upper branch of form of Sanskrit
right
you you read the based on Pakistan
inscription of of Emperor wash it sounds
like a slightly weird version of
Sanskrit you can actually understand
much of what is written even today
if you speak Hindi or any other
Indo Aryan language so-called language
you will understand significant parts of
the of the Pakistan inscription
so they assumed that maybe the old
Iranian language may have been like
Sanskrit and that's how they were able
to decipher the cuneiform portion script
and similarly there's a similar story
with the other one Mesopotamian script
the Harappan script nobody has tried
seriously to decipher it because once
the script is deciphered the entire
Aryan dravidian thing will be you know
the truth will be known
so the proponents of the Aryan Invasion
migration tourism picnic whatever Theory
it is they keep on insisting that the
so-called Harappan or the Saraswati
Hindu script
is it represented in ancient dravidian
language there are individuals like
mahadevan who came up with an
extraordinarily ridiculous
decipherment that nobody takes seriously
even the the the proponents of the Aryan
Invasion migration thing even they don't
take his desirement seriously how did he
imagine
I mean I have gone through his work the
PDFs are available online my goodness
how did he
imagine that this symbol means this how
there has to be some logic right that
everybody can understand it's no logic
he invented this disciplement so
so the claim that is made by the
proponents of the Aryan migration
tourism
theory is that the saraswati's
hinduscript represents a dravidian
language a so-called turbidian language
the dravidian language family is an
imaginary language family dreamed up by
by our Colonial
occupiers
so once this script is properly
deciphered we will know for sure which
language it encodes a script is a
vehicle
it's not a language
for instance you can write Sanskrit in
the devanagari script in the brahmi
script in the Karoshi script in the
Tibetan script in the in the Mongolian
boot script
in the in the Cambodian script
in the Tamil script so a script is
merely a vehicle it is not a language
right
so once we decipher
the Saraswati Sindhu script
will be able to read what's written
there
and I think one of the Prime reasons why
they are not trying to decipher it
seriously is they are afraid of what
language you will emerge out of it
yeah so that's why
but I I think somebody recently I don't
know the real name of the person is his
name he or she his name is yajna devam
on Twitter they I still haven't studied
their work properly but they say that
they have deciphered it and it they say
it's Sanskrit what's written is sanskrit
so I'll I'll have to spend some time and
look into this you know so yeah so
that's why those scripts were deciphered
and this one they have tried their best
not to decipher it
okay we are reaching the two hour mark I
need to take one or two questions more
swapnel says after massive asteroid
collided with our planet resulting in a
substantial loss of material in the
formation of our moon
how did the Earth regain its spherical
shape over time additionally do all the
planets in our solar system have the
same round shape as depicted in pictures
and textbooks see yeah one of the Prime
theories one of the main theories
about how the moon was formed is that
there was an ancient protoplanet in the
very early solar system that collided
with the Earth it was most likely a
glancing Collision a huge amount of
material was ejected out of
the surface of the Earth because of this
collision and it it went into orbit
around the around the earth eventually
coalesced and formed the Moon
so it was a cataclysmic Collision if
this theory is correct which formed the
moon so when such a collision would
happen between the Earth and the
slightly smaller protoplanet the entire
Earth's surface would be molten as a
consequence of this enormous Collision
it would be a health it would be all
lava so it's liquid so it very rapidly
because of gravity will will form a new
spherical shape very easy very easy
answer right so that's how it would have
happened do all the planets in our solar
system have the same spherical shape
that's the question okay let me Google
something how Maya h-a-u-m-e-a how Maya
is a
once neptunian object it's it's a dwarf
planet and take a look at this this is
the only one that does not have a
spherical shape
so it's in the Kuiper belt beyond the
orbit of Neptune
and it the reason for its weird shape
let's go to the Wikipedia article
okay let's see what it looks like okay
this thing check it out
how does this look so this uh dwarf
planet it it rotates very rapidly it
takes less than four hours to to
complete a single rotation and that's
because of this incredible rotational
speed that's why it has this weird
elongated shape it also has a couple of
rings around it can you believe it
so as far as I know this is the only uh
object you know dwarf planet or anything
else in the solar system that has a
non-pherical shape very interesting very
interesting uh what is the zombie fungus
that takes over insects through mind
control and turns them into zombies I
think it's called the cordyceps fungus
so this fungus it it enters the insect's
body through the spores that the fungus
produces and then it it it it hijacks
the nervous system of the insect and
forces this insect to do things that are
beneficial for the fungus not for the
insect it makes the insect go on a high
Branch or something and sit over there
then the fungus consumes the insect from
inside and then uses the insect's body
to release spores that will further the
process of reproduction
so yeah it hijacks the nervous system of
the of the insect it only happens to
insects as far as we know it doesn't
happen to mammals but yeah it's nice
material for a Horror Story horror movie
so it's called the cordyceps fungus
pinchuk says do you like zombie and
virus movies your top five zombie movies
uh zombie movies yeah I've I like
watching movies I've seen a bunch of
zombie movies I can think of a movie a
good movie called 28 Days Later it's
it's set in London England I believe
there is a funny movie called Shone of
the dead of the dead that's again said
in England I think there is World War Z
Brad Pitt that's a good movie Resident
Evil with Mila jovic that's a good movie
it's about zombies as well and and and
the super intelligent computer as well
uh there is Zombieland featuring Woody
Harrelson and of course the movie that
started it All Night of the Living Dead
I think it was the 1970s or 1980s most
likely 1970s maybe even 1960s Night of
the Living Dead yeah I've seen a bunch
of zombie movies and some of them are
enjoyable some of them are very
predictable and boring but yeah I'd say
it's a it's a fun genre if it is done
right okay I have many more questions
but I will take some questions from the
live chat now maybe two three questions
two three questions from the live chat
let's take a look
yeah yeah okay I saw it like I don't
know a long long time ago I found it
funny at the time maybe if I see it
again
uh see these things are subjective
okay ramai Raj Singh says Indian City
Planning is atrocious which country or
model can modern day India take
inspiration from I would say that Modern
India needs to take inspiration from the
city planning that was done
region five thousand five thousand six
thousand years ago if you look at the
kind of town planning City Planning we
had in harappa mohenjo daro Kali Mangan
um all these cities even the small towns
it was brilliant
very well planned cities were laid out
in a grid structure every house was
connected to a drainage system the
drainage system still works last year
there were floods in Pakistan
temporarily Pakistan
and you know it was reported in the news
that the whole much of Pakistan was
flooded but in the city of Mohenjo-daro
in the city of mohenjo daro the flood
waters were drained out by the 5 000
year old drainage system
so we should take inspiration from our
own past we came up with the concept of
a grid system of cloud town of City
Planning we had incredibly well planned
cities
five thousand years before anybody else
in the west even dreamed of that so
that's what we need to take inspiration
from Modern inspiration should take
Inspire Modern India should take
inspiration from the past of India
itself from our own past
says what do you think about today's
hype hyper hyposexual Society in the
sexual degeneracy that's plaguing our
human consciousness I think it's all
coming from one nation in the west which
is the United States everything is about
sex over there
they have 78 genders or 300 genders
but only two political clinicians how
does that work
you know you're either with me or you're
a Nazi you're either on my side or
you're a fascist so they see politics in
black and white only two political
inclinations but genders are about 600
700 genders and everything is about sex
over there everything it's crazy
everything is so superficial
so it's a huge problem and and they're
now trying to export it worldwide their
so-called values and culture they have
no values and no culture
so it's a huge problem I would urge
non-western even I mean I would I would
urge everybody look we are all this we
are all
sharing this planet
this East and West divide it's all
artificial
we all have the same ancestors you go
back to 100 000 years we all have the
same ancestors whether we're black white
brown whatever
right we are the same people
we are in this together we need to stop
creating these artificial divisions and
all and I would urge all right thinking
people with a sane mind to reject this
nonsense
70 million genders and God knows what
else
the purpose of human life is with this
more to human life than sex
right
so yeah it's it's terrible it's very
unfortunate what's happening and they're
trying to export this madness worldwide
okay let us see some more
a couple more questions Mingming says
hello
uh are the people from arunachal Pradesh
Tibetans because the sixth was was from
uh
and it is said that the lilama can only
be from Tibet
look uh the people of arunachal Pradesh
have a strong Affinity of the Tibetan
people culture is to some extent similar
to Tibetan culture uh genetically
ethnically they may have some Affinity
with the people up to bed as well and
you know borders change we have to
understand one thing that if you look at
the history of the world if you look at
the history of the world through Maps
borders are artificial lines that keep
on changing and evolving and going up
and down back and forth
so at some point in time what is now
some of it was then part of the kingdom
of Tibet and we know that the sixth the
sixth was born in tawang which is part
of arunachal Pradesh India so from that
perspective from our perspective since
the sixth Dalai Lama came from India
well we can lay claim to the bet not the
other way round the Chinese ever have
never been
the masts of Tibet until 1950 or
whatever right
so uh
so that's my perspective
yeah borders keep changing and the
borders will change in the future as
well our borders were drawn by Outsiders
in 1947 then our own leaders through
their miscalculations and their naivete
allowed borders to again change in 1948
Etc again in 1950s 1962 and so on well
in the future we will have stronger
leaders things will change again
so that's how it is so we cannot say
this or that from my perspective if the
sixth Dalai Lama came from India then
the whole of tibetism is Indian I can
make that claim the same logic the
Chinese use you know so yeah there is
that
Amit Kumar says should India join NATO
plus no never ever ever
NATO is the North Atlantic Treaty
Organization
Atlantic where's the Atlantic Ocean
and and even if they expand NATO all the
way to the Pacific Ocean through the
Indian Ocean what
Advantage does it give India
what benefit does it give India joining
NATO do you know the conditions for
joining NATO
do you know why France is has never been
comfortable with NATO
is because you have to
place your military under a centralized
command on NATO command are you willing
are you my dear friend Indian friends
are you willing to place the Indian
Armed Forces under a centralized NATO
command
the answer is very simple there is no
reason for India to join NATO
um
Harry says are the rajputs of other
states the same as rajputs of Rajasthan
look this is in the term rajput is kind
of a new term it's
it's about a thousand or so years old it
means rajyaputra it means you are a
member of a
a royal lineage
that's what it means
um
so uh
there are traditionally it has
traditionally been said that there are
36 Royal
Clans in India right that fellow what's
his name James Todd Also may put out a
list of 36 royal families a royal clans
of India and these are typically taken
to be the rajput lineages okay and this
is a new term that has existed for
roughly A Thousand Years
if you look at 580 or 1500 BC or
whatever it is nobody called themselves
rajputs but you still had the same
lineage as most likely the ancient
lineages that perhaps sprang from the
era of the
vedikira perhaps who knows who knows
what the story is because we've lost all
our ancient historical records so these
are all two days let's say let's talk
about today's rajput lineages these most
likely descend from those 36 Royal Clans
or whatever it was called and it doesn't
mean that they are all the same I am
sure they will have some kind of
connection you know uh
royal family is typically married among
other royal families for example the the
shindes sindhas of gwalior married with
the royal family of Nepal
who are also rajputs or whatever that
sort of thing so it's not like we are
all the same we are over all the same
people
and we all have some some blood
relations whether we know it or not
okay that should be the last questions
for today because we have crossed two
hours in 10 minutes so I'm gonna end it
over here I know lots of people are
asking questions I can see the questions
I really really apologize to all of you
I can't take everyone's questions uh but
I will keep on doing this as much as
possible next week again there will be
no live stream because I am again
traveling
for doing something interesting of
course but I will I will I will lead
more questions from you so the live
stream won't happen next week but I will
need your questions so I'm gonna put out
another communique on the uh
on the community tab for that okay so
thank you very much for the questions
always fun doing these live streams
always fun interacting with you all and
I will keep on doing this for the
foreseeable future we're gonna keep on
doing this thank you very much have a
great time have a good night good day
Wherever You Are
and I'll see you soon thank you bye